New York State Council of Churches Records
New York State Council of Churches Records
1934-1977
New York State Council of Churches.
16 linear ft.
Correspondence, agendas, minutes, memoranda, reports, printed material, and other papers relating to the Council's positions on such legislative issues as abortion, church and state relations, civil rights, family relations, labor, pornography, and Christian education.
149392
Biographical History
The New York State Council of Churches is an outgrowth of the mid-nineteenth century State Sunday School Association which was incorporated in 1889 as the New York State Sunday School Association. In 1930, its field no longer being limited to Sunday schools, the organization's name was changed to the New York State Council of Religious Education. In the late 1930's, this group joined with a State Council of churches, then in its infancy, and after the merger in 1938 became known as the New York State Council of Churches.
Today, the New York State Council of Churches is an organization of twenty-one Protestant denominations in the state, active in the fields of Christian education, youth programs, legislation and migrant worker welfare. It serves pastors through training programs, is the recognized state agency for Protestant chaplain appointments for New York State institutions and gives aid to town and country churches in building Christian communities.
The program, budget and leadership of The Council is determined by action taken at the Annual Assembly which consists of 121 delegates from constituent denominational groups and 70 additional delegates appointed by councils of churches at the city or county level. Constituent bodies are further represented through membership on the Board of Directors and in program divisions. A staff of seven at the State Council office in Syracuse includes (1) a General Secretary, (2) an Associate General Secretary, and (3) a Director of Endowment Development and Press Secretary as well as program directors for (4) Christian Education, (5) Life and Work, (6) Church Planning and Mission and (7) Church Planning and Development, the last named office combined with that of Director of Leisure Time Commission.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Administrative files contain meeting minutes, mailings, notes, memos, reports, summaries, and other assorted items relating to administrative functions of the organization.
The New York State Council of Churches Records, consisting of correspondence, mimeographed material and a small number of manuscripts, is divided into three groups according to office of origin, titled Associate General Secretary's Office, Division of Christian Education and Division of Church Planning & Mission. There are also two general groups, Administrative files and Correspondence, general.
The material from the Associate General Secretary's Office includes the correspondence of Theodore L. Conklin, associate general secretary of the Council, typescript minutes of meetings, manuscripts by Theodore L. Conklin, Dean M. Kelley, Harry Confoy, Paul W. Rishell, Lewis N. Powell and Arthur Mielke, and miscellaneous mimeographed material such as memoranda, minutes, agenda, and reports. All the material is arranged alphabetically by subject and pertains to New York State legislative issues and bills, the New York State 1967 Constitutional Convention issues, annual meetings, committee meetings, staff meetings, Business Administration Commission meetings, legislative seminars, Human Rights Commission activities, Legislative Commission activities, legislative seminars, migrant ministry activities, public relations and development and related subjects. Also included are a chronological file of mimeographed material, 1966-1969, issued by The Council and a file of the State Council Reporter, 194}1968, published by the Council. Folders containing correspondence are appropriately labeled. Significant correspondents include Leon M. Adkins, Jr., 1963-1966; James E. Allen, Jr., 1963-1966; Edwin T. Dahlberg, 1959-1963; J. Ralph Davie, 1954-1958; Robert R. Douglass, 1966; James A. Farley, 1966; Lawrence J. Holt, 1964-1967; Lee A. Howe, Jr., 1960-1961; Robert F. Kennedy, 1966; John V.P. Lassoe, Jr., 1965-1967; Stuart MacMacklin, 1959-1964; Arthur Mielke, 1965-1967; Bishop Malcolm Peabody, 1956-1959; Dutton S. Peterson, 1958-1964; Fred N. Poulton, 1965; Paul W. Rishell, 1957-1966; Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1960-1967; William E. Smith, 1959-1960; Ralph W. Sockman, 1958; John H. Terry, 1966-1967; Anthony J. Travia, 1959-1966 and A. Pennington Whitehead, 1953-1954.
Correspondence, general contains general correspondence, not part of any specific department.
The Division of Christian Education material, 1954-1968, consists of mimeographed material and one letter, arranged alphabetically by subject. The subjects covered are related to the division's Adult Commission, Children's Commission, Higher Education Commission, Leadership Education Division, Youth Commission and Youth Security Commission. Memoranda, minutes of meetings and reports are included.
The Division of Church Planning Mission material, 1966-1968, consists of a small group of mimeographed reports.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically within each series.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to New York church and clergy. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; New York State; Religion and philosophy; Activism and social reform; New York State Council of Churches -- Archives.; Abortion.; Alcoholism.; Christianity and politics.; Church and state.; Civil rights.; Domestic relations -- New York (State); Drug addiction.; Federal aid to education.; Lobbyists -- New York (State); Lotteries -- Law and legislation -- New York (State); Migrant labor.; Religion and state.; Prayer in the public schools -- Law and legislation -- New York (State); Religion in the public schools.; Bills (legislative records); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Phonograph records.; Reports.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
1970: Collection may not be used without the written permission of the general secretary of the New York State Community of Churches (formerly the New York State Council of Churches). Any such written permission documents will be retained by SCRC.
Acquisition Information
Gift of New York State Council of Churches, October, 1968, 1970, 1977.
Inventory
- Administrative files
  - [General], 1968-1970 Mar; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], 1970 Apr-1971; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - [General], 1972-1973; 7 folders (Box 3)
  - [General], 1974-1977; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Returned mail, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Associate General Secretary's Office
  1970: The collection may not be used without the written permission of the general secretary of the New York State Community of Churches (formerly the New York State Council of Churches). Any such written permission documents will be retained by SCRC.
  - History and Constitution of the Council (Box 4)
  - Abortion law, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Aging, problems of the, 1959-1960 (Box 5)
  - Aid to education (federal), 1961 (Box 5)
  - Aid to education (state), 1961 (Box 5)
  - Air Force Manual charge, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Alcoholic beverage control laws, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
  - Alcoholism, 1953-1955 (Box 5)
  - Association of Council Secretaries, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Baptist Commission on Social Relations, 1954-1958 (Box 6)
  - Bingo, undated (Box 6)
  - Birth control, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Boy Scouts of America (Box 6)
  - Budget planning (Box 6)
  - Business Administration Commission, 1951-1965; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Business Administration Commission, 1966-1969 (Box 7)
  - Capital punishment, 1934-1962; includes statement on capital punishment by Theodore L. Conklin, typescript (Box 7)
  - Centennial campaign (Box 7)
  - Champlain Valley, 350th anniversary celebration
    - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, includes "Out of the North Country" by Lewis N. Powell, typescript copy (Box 7)
  - Church-state parochial schools, 1959-1961 (Box 7)
  - Churchmen's International Consultation, 1965-1968 (Box 8)
  - Civil rights, 1963 (Box 8)
  - Civilian defense chaplains, 1953-1960 (Box 8)
  - Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State, 1967
    - Correspondence, Oct 1966-Oct 1967; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Minutes and meetings (Box 8)
    - Statements by Theodore L. Conklin, Arthur Mielke and others, typescript drafts (Box 8)
    - Position papers (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - News clippings (Box 9)
  - Cooperstown proposal (Box 9)
  - Denominational-interdenominational staff conferences
    - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Endowment campaign, 1961-1962 (Box 9)
  - Equal Moral Standard Amendment, 1963-1964 (Box 10)
  - Family justice, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Finance promotion data, 1954-1958 (Box 10)
  - Gambling
    - Correspondence, 1954-1962 (Box 10)
    - News clippings, 1951-1965; 3 folders (Box 10)
    - News clippings, undated (Box 10)
  - Health and welfare (Box 11)
  - Hospital employees, 1963 (Box 11)
  - Human Rights Commission
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 11)
    - Report to the governor, Jan-Mar 1968; typescript reproductions, three drafts (A, B, C) (Box 11)
  - Keuka College National Development Program, 1964-1965 (Box 11)
  - Legislative Commission
    - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1966; undated; 8 folders (Box 12)
    - Minutes and meetings, 1966 (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1966 (Box 13)
  - Legislative Commission releases, 1955-1963; typescript copies and reproductions; 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Legislative Commission releases, 1964 (Box 14)
  - Legislative seminars, 1951-1964; 7 folders (Box 14)
  - Legislative seminars, 1965 (Box 15)
  - Lisle Fellowship, 1965-1966 (Box 15)
  - Lottery
    - [General]
      - Correspondence, Jun 1965-Dec 1966; 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous, includes "Why Take A Chance" by Paul W. Rishell; typescript and printed material, revisions (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
      - News clippings (Box 16)
    - Committee of 100,000 Against the Lottery Amendment
      - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous, includes memorandum opposing Lottery Amendment by Theodore L. Conklin, typescript (Box 16)
    - National, 1957-1958 (Box 16)
    - New York City, 1966 (Box 16)
    - State Committee Against
      - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Mass communications (Box 17)
  - Matrimonial and family laws, 1959-1963 (Box 17)
  - Meetings
    - Annual Assembly, 1946-1962; 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Annual Assembly, 1963-1966; 4 folders (Box 18)
    - Board of Directors, Executive Committee, 1966 (Box 18)
    - Staff, 1963-1965; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Staff, 1966-1968 (Box 19)
    - Trustees, 1954 (Box 19)
  - Migrant Ministry, includes photographs (Box 19)
  - Mimeographed material, Dec 1966-Jun 1967; 4 folders (Box 19)
  - Mimeographed material, Jul 1967-Dec 1968; 7 folders (Box 20)
  - Mimeographed material, 1969 (Box 21)
  - Narcotics, 1960 (Box 21)
  - National Council of Churches, 1950 (Box 21)
  - New York Board of Rabbis, 1958 (Box 21)
  - New York State Assembly and Senate bills relating to labor (Box 21)
  - New York State Assembly bills, 1966
    - Intro. 2-1432 (Box 21)
    - Intro. 1438-2889 (Box 21)
    - Intro. 2909-4053 (Box 22)
    - Intro. 4056-4673 (Box 22)
  - New York State Senate bills, 1966
    - Intro. 23-1346 (Box 22)
    - Intro. 1349-2620 (Box 22)
    - Intro. 2661-3953 (Box 22)
    - Intro. 3954-4877 (Box 23)
  - New York State Assembly and Senate joint bills, 1966
    - Intro. 395-4798 (Box 23)
  - New York State Legislature bill summaries, 1958-1966; 9 folders (Box 23)
  - New York State Legislature bill summaries, 1967 (Box 24)
  - New York State Women's Relief Corps Home, 1959-1960 (Box 24)
  - Nominating commission, 1961-1963 (Box 24)
  - Nuclear warfare (Box 24)
  - Obscene literature, 1961 (Box 24)
  - The One Hundred Club, 1958 (Box 24)
  - Parental responsibility (Box 24)
  - Penal law and criminal code (Box 24)
  - Policy Committee, 1953-1961; 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Prayer in the schools
    - Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, includes "Supreme Court on Prayer - the Churches React" by Dean M. Kelley and anonymous statements, typescript (Box 24)
    - News clippings (Box 25)
  - Public education, clippings (Box 25)
  - Public relations and development
    - Correspondence, 1955-1960 (Box 25)
    - Meetings and minutes (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 25)
  - Racial discrimination and segregation, 1958; includes "One Country, One Classroom" by Harry Confoy; "Brothers," anonymous; typescripts (Box 25)
  - Radio program, "Voice of the Rural Church", production #357; nys_church_001; phonograph disc (Box 25)
  - Radio program, "Voice of the Rural Church", production #60-16; nys_church_002; phonograph disc (Box 25)
  - Religious issue, presidential campaign, 1960 (Box 25)
  - Reports
    - Annual, 1948; 1951-1967; 4 folders (Box 26)
    - Financial, 1966-1967 (Box 26)
  - Right wing extremism, 1960 (Box 26)
  - Roswell Park Memorial Institute, 1957 (Box 26)
  - Sex education (Box 26)
  - Staff salaries and responsibilities (Box 26)
  - State Council Reporter, 1943-1959; many are photocopies; 3 folders (Box 26)
  - State Council Reporter, 1960-1969; many are photocopies; Sent to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
  - Stillwater First Baptist Church, 1955-1961 (Box 27)
  - Study Committee
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous, 1959-1961 (Box 27)
  - Sunday laws (Box 27)
  - Syracuse University American Assembly, 1967 (Box 27)
  - United Church Women of New York State (Box 27)
  - Youth in the courts, 1956-1958; includes "Dealing with Juvenile Delinquency" by Theodore L. Conklin, typescript (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous news clippings (Box 27)
- Correspondence, general
  - A-G, 7 folders (Box 28)
  - H-Q, 7 folders (Box 29)
  - R-Z, 5 folders (Box 30)
- Division of Christian Education, 1934-1968
  - General division material (Box 30)
  - Adult Commission (Box 30)
  - Camp and conference (Box 31)
  - Children's Commission (Box 31)
  - Higher Education Commission (Box 31)
  - Leadership education (Box 31)
  - Mentally retarded, religious training for (Box 31)
  - Social crisis (Box 31)
  - Vacation Church School (Box 31)
  - Weekday religious education (Box 31)
  - Young Citizens Camp (Box 31)
  - Youth Commission
    - Minutes of meetings (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous material, 1964-1965 (Box 31)
  - Youth Security Commission (Box 31)
- Division of Church Planning and Mission, 1934-1968
  - Census, religious (Box 32)
  - Federation (Box 32)
  - Leisure time (Box 32)
  - The rural church (Box 32)
    See also Radio program, "Voice of the Rural Church".
  - The Church Center (Box 32)
Selected index to correspondence
The index below lists individuals alphabetically, followed by the name of the folder in which their correspondence, either incoming or outgoing, may be found. It is not comprehensive and does not list all persons appearing in the collection.
Adkins, Leon M. Jr.Legislative Commission Legislative seminars N.Y. Board of Rabbis
Allen, James E. Jr.Denominational-interdenominational staff conferences Legislative Commission Legislative seminars Lottery: State Committee Against
Armbruster, Christian H. Legislative Commission
Associated Executive Committee of Friends on Indian Affairs Meetings: Annual Assembly
Associated Industries of New York State, Inc. Aging, problems of the
Association for the Study of Abortion, Inc. Legislative Commission
Bachman, C. Charles Roswell Park Memorial Institute
Biederstadt, F. H. Legislative seminars
Bodo, John Lottery: [General]
Bordley, James III Hospital employees
Brade, Madeleine Legislative seminars
Bronston, Jack E. Legislative Commission
Brossman, Donald G. Lottery: State Committee Against
Brydges, Earl W. Legislative Commission
Burke, Rev. Carl F. Legislative Commission
Butler, Rix Pierce Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Carothers, J. Edward Aging, problems of the
Cederberg, George S. Hospital employees
Chinn, Harvey N. Lottery: [General]
Clark, Stephen C. Cooperstown proposal
Cox, David F. Lottery: [General]
Corbin, Sol Neil Legislative Commission
Dahlberg, Edwin T.Champlain Valley 350th Legislative seminars
Davie, J. Ralph Baptist Commission
Debevoice, Eli WhitneyHuman Rights Commission Legislative seminars
Dick, James M. Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Dirks, Howard M.Finance promotion data Public relations and development
Douglass, Robert R. Legislative Commission
East Harlem Protestant Parish Narcotics
Edgar, Richard P.Lottery: [General] Lottery: Committee of 100,000 Against the Lottery Amendment
Farley. James A. Lottery: State Committee Against
Flick, Hugh C. Legislative seminars
Fowell, Myron W. Lottery: State Committee Against
Gatland, Franklin Z. Legislative Commission
Gemmer, Robert Lottery: State Committee Against
Gordon, Harold Alcoholic beverage control laws
Greenberg, Lester Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Hale, John P. Lottery: State Committee Against
Harrington, Donald Szantho Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Hecht, Burton Legislative Commission
Hesson, Samuel M. Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Hodges, Graham R.Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State Legislative seminars
Holland, Hugh P. Legislative Commission
Holt, Lawrence J.Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State Legislative Commission Legislative seminars Lottery: State Committee Against
Home Advisory Council of New York, Inc. [not given]
Howe, Lee A.Meetings: Annual Assembly Study Committee
Hughes, John H. Alcoholic beverage control laws
Hunter, William H. Legislative Commission
Hurley, Thomas F. Civilian defense chaplains
Isham, Howard E. The One Hundred Club
Javits, Jacob K. (Senator) Meetings: Annual Assembly
Johnson, Douglas Public relations and development
Joint Legislative Committee to Study the Publication and Dissemination of Offensive and Obscene Material Legislative Commission
Keating, Kenneth B. (Senator) Meetings: Annual Assembly
Kelly, H. Hugh Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Kennedy, Robert F. (Senator)Lottery: [General] Lottery: Committee of 100,000 Against the Lottery Amendment
King, Martin Luther, Jr. Legislative seminars
Lamb, Charles F. Prayer in schools
Lassoe, John V. P., Jr.Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State Family justice Legislative Commission
Levitt, Arthur Legislative seminars
Little, M. V. Legislative seminars
Lombardi, Tarky Jr. Legislative Commission
MacMackin, StuartBirth control Legislative Commission Legislative seminars Meetings: Annual Assembly Obscene literature Prayer in schools
Mahoney, Francis J.Legislative Commission Legislative seminars
Mahoney, Walter J.Legislative seminars Lottery: State Committee Against
Marshall, Thurgood Legislative seminars
Martin, J. Dean (Reverend) Hospital employees
Metcalf, George R.Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State Legislative seminars
Mielke, ArthurConstitutional Convention Committee, New York State Legislative Commission
Modisher, Donald E. Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Moore, Frank Lottery: State Committee Against
Moore, James A. G.Aging, problems of the Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Moore, Robert E. Legislative seminars
Murphy, George A. Legislative Commission
National Council of Churches Legislative Commission
Nevin, Hugh G. Jr. Legislative Commission
New York Farm Bureau Alcoholic beverage control laws
New York Dept. of State, Division of Corporations Meetings: Trustees
New York State Congress of Parents & Teachers Legislative Commission
New York State Council on Crime and Delinquency Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
New york State Grange Alcoholic beverage control laws
New York Temperance Civic League, Inc.Alcoholic beverage control laws Legislative Commission
New York State Youth Commission Legislative seminars
Nicklas, Earle Hospital employees
Nixon, Allan Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Norton, F. Paul Lottery: State Committee Against
Peabody, Malcolm (Rt. Rev.) Finance promotion data
Peters, Robert F. R. Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Peterson, Dutton S.Alcoholic beverage control laws Legislative seminars N.Y. Board of Rabbis The One Hundred Club
Poulton, Fred N. Churchmen's International Consultation
Powell, Lewis N. Champlain Valley 350th
Protestant Council of the City of New York Legislative Commission
Quinlivan, James J. (Dr.) Roswell Park Memorial Institute
Rishell, Paul W.Lottery: [General] Lottery: State Committee Against Youth in the courts
Roadarmel, KennethCivilian defense chaplains
Rockefeller, Nelson A.Aging, problems of the Human Rights Commission Legislative Commission Legislative seminars
Ronan, William J. Legislative seminars
Root, Oren Legislative seminars
Schrock, Robert C. Alcoholic beverage control laws
Scott, Philip Gordon Meetings: Annual Assembly
Smith, William E.Church-state parochial schools Matrimonial and family laws
Sockman, Ralph The One Hundred Club
Stevenson, Adlai E. Legislative seminars
Strohbeck, Charles W. Abortion law
Terry, John H.Legislative Commission Lottery: Committee of 100,000 Against the Lottery Amendment
Tobin, Charles J. Jr. Alcoholic beverage control laws
Travia, Anthony J. Legislative Commission
Twentieth Century Fund Public relations and development
Wagner, Robert F. Constitutional Convention Committee, New York State
Ward, W. Ralph Denominational-interdenominational staff conferences
Webb, James M. Legislative Commission
Westchester Citizens' Committee of the National Council on Crime and Delinquency Legislative Commission
Whitehead, A. Pennington Cooperstown proposal
Wiediger, Edward H. Lottery: [General]
Wilson, Jerome L.Legislative Commission Legislative seminars The One Hundred Club